Vivekpandian Veerapandian

San Jose, CA (214) 802-4843 github.com/vivekpandian08

vivekpandian08.github.io linkedin.com/in/vivekpandian8 vivekpandian08@gmail.com medium.com/@vivekpandian08

Data Scientist with 3-years of experience in extracting customer and marketing insights from data points by building Linear and Non-Linear ML models. Proficient at framing ETL pipeline deploying end-to-end machine learning models in the Cloud.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming: Python (Scikit-learn, Pandas, Numpy, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras, OpenCV, PySpark), R, SQL, SAS

Data Visualization: Tableau, Power BI, Shiny, GGPlot2, Plotly, Streamlit, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Bokeh

Databases & Bigdata: Big Query, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, Graph, MongoDB (NoSQL), Hadoop, Hive, Spark

ML Concepts: Hypothesis Testing, A/B Testing, Forecasting, Regression, Classification, Clustering, NLP, Computer Vision

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Science Intern | R

Sept 2020 – Present

SuperWorld, United States – Augmented Reality Real Estate on Blockchain

• Developed an interactive web app in R-shiny that does real-time end to end sentiment analysis of SuperWorld's

Senior Data Scientist | Python, R, Tableau, AWS EC2, S3

Jan 2015 - June 2018

Ordermycake.in, India – E-Commerce B2C Platform to sell Bakery Products

- Generated 18% increase in revenue to \$5k in 2017 by leveraging NLP techniques to analyze customers feedback
- Built Predictive model using Decision Tree to find the likelihood of a purchase from clickstream data and optimize the model by adding new features to improve precision rate to 76%
- Designed 3 A/B tests to identify the most engaging marketing campaign, resulted in a 30% increase in sales
- Led a 10-member cross-functional team to build an end to end B2C platform to expand the **operations from 2 to 8 cities** and presented reports to stakeholders using **Tableau** charts and dashboards
- Identified 4500 potential churn customers by developing ML models and mitigated 36% by offering them discounts
- Revamped coupon mailing strategy for 3 customer segments by clustering using **K-means** and identifying the most engaging coupons leading to a **12% estimated increase in headcount**
- Recommended optimized price for products by web scraping and data mining to analyze competitor product prices,
 leading to a \$3K increase in yearly revenue
- Initiated a new payment method to solve delivery problems that satisfied customers and increased unit sales to 6.5%

Software Engineer | MySQL Mar 2012 – Sept 2014

Cluster Wireless Software, India – Developed Software which facilitates M2M communications through IoT applications

- Designed SQL queries to extract information from IoT sensor data and identified anomalies by K-means clustering
- Analyzed product pain points and collaborated with a multi-functional team to develop robust solutions to meet client requirements, increased project conversion to 30%

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Dallas - M.S., Business Analytics (Data Science Major)

3.67

Jan 2019 – Dec 2020

Project Mentor, BALC: Mentored 15 Grad Students in an Intra College ML project competition, and secured 3rd place

College of Engineering Guindy, India - *B.E., Electronics and Communication*

Aug 2007 – May 2011

PERSONAL PROJECTS (DATA SCIENCE)

Stress Detection on Social Media

Python (Natural Language Processing)

April 2020 – Aug 2020

- Leveraged **web scrapping** to scrape 30k labeled Reddit posts and extracted features by pre-training Word2Vec, Doc2Vec and BERT embeddings with 190k unlabeled posts that capture semantic and syntactic similarity among words
- Trained XGBoost and BERT models to classify Stress posts on GCP, that achieved accuracy of 92.74% and recall of 94.58%

Traffic Sign Recognition for Autonomous Driving

Python (Computer Vision)

Oct 2019 - Jan 2020

- Pre-processed images and experimented with 5 different CNN architectures using Tensorflow to classify 43 traffic signs
- Deployed an interactive web APP that classifies traffic sign from user input using Flask(REST API) and Kubernetes on GCP

Credit Card Fraud Detection

Python (Supervised Learning)

May 2019 - July 2019

 Performed data analysis, and hypothesis testing. Built an ML pipeline using python(PySpark) to predict fraud transaction using SVM, KNN, Naïve Bayes Random Forest, and Neural Networks with SMOTE resampling and achieved AUC of 0.82